<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A clear confutation of Mr. Richard Allen, and his five commendators, from their own confessions, collected out of the vindication of his essay, and fairly improv'd against them, to the overthrow of their conjoined singing in artificial tunes in gospel-worship. To which is added, an answer to Mr. William Collins's defence from the charge exhibited against him in my book, entituled, The controversie of singing brought to an end, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M692B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R180372</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614783</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175969</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2757:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A clear confutation of Mr. Richard Allen, and his five commendators, from their own confessions, collected out of the vindication of his essay, and fairly improv'd against them, to the overthrow of their conjoined singing in artificial tunes in gospel-worship. To which is added, an answer to Mr. William Collins's defence from the charge exhibited against him in my book, entituled, The controversie of singing brought to an end, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
                  <author>Marlow, Isaac. The controversie of singing brought to an end.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Isaac Marlow.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>R. A. --  (Richard Allen). --  Essay to prove singing of psalms with conjoin'd voices a Christian duty.</term>
               <term>Keach, Benjamin, 1640-1704. --  The breach repaired in God's worship.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Music in churches --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Psalmody --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175969:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A CLEAR CONFUTATION OF M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Richard Allen, And his Five Commendators, From their own Confeſſions, collected out of the Vindication of his <hi>Eſſay,</hi> and fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improv'd againſt them, to the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of their Conjoined Singing in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Tunes in Goſpel-Worſhip.</head>
            <head type="sub">To which is added, An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence from the Charge exhibited againſt him in my Book, Entituled, <hi>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie of Singing brought to an end,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THere being ſo much already ſaid in my former Treatiſes, to the Argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Part of the Controverſie of Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and having in my laſt Diſcourſe I publiſhed brought it to an End, for my own part I ſee but little or nothing elſe to do, than to clear it at the end, and ſo to finiſh my preſent Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175969:2"/>for the Truth. And that I may do it the more effectually, I ſhall firſt anſwer ſome few Exceptions in Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Reply to me, which I think are moſt material to clear the way for a full Confutation of his Error from his own Confeſſions. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſaith in <hi>page</hi> 59. <q>That there is no Evidence in the Text, (<hi>Exod.</hi> 15.21.) that either theſe Dances or Muſical Inſtruments were uſed by them in the Church of God as ſuch, but thoſe Dances of the Women with Muſick (mentioned <hi>ver.</hi> 20.) ſeem plainly to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of as a Conſequence of their Religious Thankſgiving in the Church-Aſſembly, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the foregoing part of the Chapter.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I have ſufficiently proved in my laſt, as well as in my other Treatiſes of ſinging, that <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> did not ſing vocally together; For, 1. Some part of the Song, <hi>Judges</hi> 5.7. (viz. <hi>until that I Deborah aroſe, that I aroſe a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Iſrael</hi>) was not proper for <hi>Barak</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs. 2. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Awake, awake De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah, awake, awake, utter a Song: Ariſe Barak, and lead thy captivity captive, thou Son of Abinoam;</hi> which Expreſſions ſhew, that this Song was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by <hi>Deborah,</hi> and part of it to <hi>Barak,</hi> and ſo all of it was not proper matter for <hi>Barak</hi> to expreſs; and alſo that this was ſung at the ſame time before <hi>Barak</hi> had led his captivity away; and yet in <hi>ver.</hi> 1. 'tis ſaid, <hi>Then ſang Deborah and Barak,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo in <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Then ſang Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the Children of Iſrael;</hi> yet it does not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſang all vocally together, any more than that <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> ſang with conjoin'd voices, which we find they did
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175969:2"/>not; neither does it from thence follow, that the Womens ſinging with Timbrels and Dances, ſeperate from the Men, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20. was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards at a different Seaſon, any more than if we ſhould againſt the Light of Scripture ſuppoſe, that <hi>Barak</hi> join'd in ſpirit with <hi>Deborah</hi> in the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of her Song, at a different Seaſon, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had led his captivity away. Beſides, as there is nothing expreſſed that lays a foundation for this Objection, ſo there is reaſon to believe that the Women ſang with Timbrels and Dances at the ſame time when <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſang, <hi>v.</hi> 1. ſeeing that as 'tis ſaid <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſang <hi>to the Lord,</hi> ſo alſo <hi>Miriam</hi> began the Song <hi>to the Lord,</hi> which ſhews that <hi>Miriam</hi>'s and the Womens ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was as much a religious Thankſgiving to the Lord, as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s was, <hi>ver.</hi> 1, &amp;c. and at the ſame ſeaſon, and not afterwards.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To what Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> in <hi>page</hi> 59. ſays con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my Authors, which ſhew the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Greek</hi> Word <hi>Hymneo,</hi> (which is ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to praiſe or give thanks, and alſo to lament or complain) I ſhall here anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he plainly owns that the word <hi>Hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo</hi> is not limited in its ſignification to Songs of Praiſe, but he ſtrives to prove that its moſt proper ſignification is to ſing praiſe, which I deny, and have produced witneſs enough againſt it; and there is no need to contend about it, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our laſt Tranſlators have rendred the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> Word <hi>Tehillah,</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> Word <hi>Hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos,</hi> in the Old Teſtament, ſimply Praiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By his picking out of ſeveral of my Authors (which render the word <hi>Hymneo</hi> various ways) ſome expreſſions that renders it to ſing a Hymn
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175969:3"/>or Praiſe, and by his improving thoſe that ſpeak moſt in this Language, he has laboured to raiſe a duſt, that their Teſtimony ſhould not be ſo clearly diſcerned.</p>
            <p>But Obſerve, he has not, neither can he charge me with any falſe Citation of them, and ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſtroy the Evidence I bring them for, nor the fuller and clearer Teſtimony of the reſt of my Authors that are noted in my little Tract, where I have only briefly mentioned them, and not largely cited the Evidence of ſeveral of them, whoſe Teſtimonies were more fully given be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my prelimited Forms, and in my Reply to Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> to which I refer the Reader, if he pleaſe, for further Satisfaction, in this and many other matters that I could not treat of in ſo ſmall a Tract on Singing as I lately publiſhed, with my Remarks on Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s <hi>Eſſay.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays, <hi>page</hi> 61. <q>That the Learned Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> does not tranſlate the word (as our Author repreſents him) ſimply praiſe, (as if it ſignified no more) but he tells us (on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.) that there be three kinds of Songs mentioned in this Book, of which one (he tells us) is called <hi>Tehillah,</hi> in <hi>Greek Hymnos,</hi> a Hymn or Praiſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis true, Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> ſays that there be three kinds of Songs in that Book of <hi>Pſalms, viz.</hi> Pſalms, Hymns and Songs; but tho' he calls them all Songs, whatever Titles they bare, yet it is becauſe they were all Songs for Temple-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and not from the ſignification of every Title; for ſome of the Pſalms, <hi>viz. Pſalm</hi> 17, and 86, and 90, and 102. are entituled a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175969:3"/>of <hi>David,</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp;c. which denote the nature of thoſe Pſalms or Temple-Songs to be Prayer, and not that they are Songs from their Title of Prayer; and ſo the word in <hi>Hebrew, Tehillah,</hi> Greek, <hi>Hymnos,</hi> ſignifies the nature of the Pſalm or Song to be a Praiſe, as the word is ſimply and rightly tranſlated by Mr. <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> who tranſlates it in the Pſalms, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the word in his Annotations on them in eight ſeveral places ſingly or ſimply to praiſe,<note place="margin">See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.171. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.14. <hi>Annot. Pſal.</hi> 1. <hi>An. Pſ.</hi> 145. <hi>An. Pſal.</hi> 3.</note> and I cannot find that he renders it in any one place a Song of Praiſe, or to ſing praiſe, but ſingly to praiſe. And therefore Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> has done ill to joyn with Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my former complaint, which is now juſtly againſt them both, with the reſt of their Companions, for abuſing my Author in ſo plain a caſe, as renders them very unfair in their dealing with me.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> in <hi>page</hi> 71. ſays, <q>The Divine Pſalmiſts do often not only ſpeak of their own ſinging the Divine Praiſes, but alſo call upon others to joyn with them therein; ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.2, 11. and 27.6. and 145.7. and 146.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which plainly ſhews that the People were to do more than barely ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> Pſal. 34.4. and 33.1, 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Theſe being all the Scriptures I find he brings to prove, that the People ſang vocally together with the <hi>Levites</hi> in the Inſtituted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God under the Law, I ſhall briefly reply in general, That for <hi>David</hi> to ſay, <hi>I will ſing praiſes to the Lord,</hi> and to exhort the righteous to ſing, and ſuch like Expreſſions are ſometimes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175969:4"/>to be taken of <hi>David</hi>'s perſonating of Chriſt, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.49. applied to Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.9. ſometimes of Miſterious Prophecies to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled at or in the glorious day of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom yet to come, and ſome to thoſe Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times which had the Spiritual Gift of ſinging, when the Saints did ſing in Spirit together by the ſingle voice of their Miniſter, according to Goſpel-Rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15, 16, 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thoſe Scriptures that relate to <hi>David</hi> perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the righteous in his day, muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as its ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> 2 Chron. 7.6. that <hi>David</hi> praiſed the Lord by the Miniſtry, or Hand of the <hi>Levites,</hi> and that the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did not vocally ſing with their Levites and Singers, is alſo confirmed by the Office or Order of Singers, that ſinging in the publick worſhip of God was confined to under the Law, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16, to 25. and by the Peoples ſaying no more after the Levites had done ſinging than <hi>Amen, praſe ye Lord,</hi> Pſal. 106.48. Deut. 27.14, 15. ſo that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> is not able to bring one Text of Scripture in the whole Bible to prove that ever the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſang together with their ſinging Levites; and altho' thoſe Miniſters under the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament might ſing more than their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, yet this is no warrant for others to do the like under the Goſpel: Becauſe, the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Worſhip and Service was a formal, carnal, ſhadowy and prophetical Miniſtration, 'till the time of Goſpel-reformation, and the Heavenly Things themſelves were come, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1, 9, 10, 23. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.12.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> in <hi>page</hi> 76, 77. to juſtifie his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175969:4"/>for Art in Singing, <hi>viz.</hi> That much art was uſed by the Holy Pen-men of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in writing them, he asks me, whether holy Men of God could write the Scriptures without the Art of Writing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. They were required by the Holy Ghoſt to write the Scriptures, but Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> is no way required by the Lord to make uſe of writing, or any other Art, to practice his way of Singing. Beſides, tho' the Holy Pen-men of Scripture might uſe the art of writing to record them for us, yet the matter of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo delivered, was formed by the inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and movings of the Holy Ghoſt, and not meerly by humane art, as Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Songs are, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Before I proceed farther, I ſhall take ſome Notice of what Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays, <hi>pag.</hi> 33. concerning thoſe three Hebrew Words, <hi>viz. Halelu eth jehovah,</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Bible, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 148.1. which Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> in his Eſſay left out in citing that verſe, to make it look like Hebrew Rhime and Metre; ſaith he, <q>I did not omit them on purpoſe to make it Rhime, is plain, in that inſtead of four lines a rhime, as I have there ſet it down, there are ſix if thoſe words are put in.</q> To which I briefly anſwer, That 'tis eaſie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate this to be a cheat from Mr. <hi>Allens</hi> own words, for ſeeing he makes the three <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> words left out before now into one line or verſe by themſelves, for the ſecond line of his ſix, and cuts off the word <hi>Hallelujah</hi> from the firſt line that was of his four lines before, to make it by it ſelf the firſt line of his ſix lines now, then either his five lines that he made but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175969:5"/>four lines before, or the four lines muſt be a wrong to the Rhime and Metre as he cites them for in the ſacred Text: For if it be, as he ſays, Rhime and Metre in the Hebrew Bible, it muſt be ſo as we find it there without alteration, and therefore for him to make four lines of verſes in Rhime in one book, and five lines of verſes in Rhime in another Book of the ſame matter, is ſuch an alteration, that renders it a plain Cheat either in his four lines or in his five lines of verſes. And by this one inſtance the unlearned Reader may eaſily gueſs at the reſt of his Hebrew Rhyming, eſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering he does not tye it to any equal order of Metre. And the true reaſon of it muſt be, becauſe the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> (nor the Songs of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Deborah,</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi>) are not in Rhime in the Hebrew Bible, as I have ſhewed in my laſt Treatiſe, from the Teſtimony of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Jews</hi> learned in the Hebrew Tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Having hitherto been removing thoſe Exceptions that were neceſſary to take ſome notice of, I ſhall now proceed to the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s practiſe of ſinging, from his own Confeſſions; and in order thereunto I ſhall here premiſe, That</p>
            <p>Thoſe five Commendators of Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Vindication of his <hi>Eſſay,</hi> viz. <hi>Joſeph Maiſters, William Collins, Joſeph Stennet, John Piggot</hi> and <hi>Thomas Harriſon,</hi> do in their Epiſtle ſay, <q>Tho' the Author of the Animadverſions on Mr. <hi>Allens</hi> Eſſay, — has thought meet to let fly — at us who ſubſcribed a Preface to that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, for no other crime than that of commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Subject of it to the Reader, and of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175969:5"/>our Opinion of the ability of its Author to ſpeak for himſelf on that Argument, with out needing our Recommendation, we are neither afraid nor aſhamed to let the World know, that we have yet ſeen no Reaſon to retract our words, and we dare venture to ſay as much of this Reply.</q> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That theſe Words, <hi>viz. For no other crime than that — of giving our Opinion of the ability of its Author to ſpeak for himſelf:</hi> Altho' they are brought in as the cauſe of Dr. <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fly at them, yet I do not find that he has in that manner expreſt himſelf in any part of his Book: And therefore I conclude, that thoſe words are the five Commendators own Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as 'tis further confirmed by that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>viz. We are neither afraid nor aſhamed to let the world know, that we have yet ſeen no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to retract our words:</hi> For theſe Expreſſions relating to the Fore-going words implies an Aſſertion of them to be their own, <hi>viz.</hi> That [they] gave their Opinion of the ability of its Author (<hi>i. e.</hi> of the Eſſay) to ſpeak for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: So that it ſollows,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in theſe words of the aforeſaid five Commendators, there is a falſe Inſinuation, for they not only implicitely ſay that they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the Subject of that Eſſay, but that they gave their Opinion of the ability of its Author to ſpeak for himſelf on that Argument, without needing their Recommendation, which how true this is, the Reader may judge from their own Words in their former Preface to Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Eſſay, where they ſay, <q>How well he has acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175969:6"/>himſelf in the management of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is by himſelf ſubmitted to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the world in his publication of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We ſhall only ſay, that as 'tis not our Buſineſs to uſe many Words, to prepoſſeſs the Reader in his Favour, ſo 'tis our Opinion, that the Book is able to ſpeak for it ſelf, and needs not our Suffrage to recommend it.</q> So that thoſe five Miniſters have begun their Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Recommendation to Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a falſe Inſinuation, that in their la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Preface they gave their Opinion of the Ability of the Author to ſpeak for himſelf, without need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Recommendation, when in truth they ſaid it of the Book it ſelf, diſtinguiſhed by them from the Author. Now I cannot conceive why they ſhould utter this falſe Inſinuation, unleſs it be to ſqueez themſelves from under their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute commendations of thoſe Errors in Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Eſſay, which are juſtly charged upon them. But ſurely no ſober judicious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans will either take this falſe Inſinuation for the leaſt acknowledgment, or publick ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the wrong they have done our Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or the Truth, or will from this latter Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face diſcharge them from thoſe Errors which they have without exceptions recommended in their former Preface to Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Eſſay: Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially conſidering, that in their laſt to his Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, <q>They ſtoutly tell us, that they are neither afraid nor aſhamed to let the World know, that they have ſeen no reaſon to retract their former Words, and alſo that they dare adventure to ſay as much for this his Reply.</q> So that I conclude from their former Preface, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175969:6"/>in their laſt, wherein they likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Vindication of his Eſſay, that both his Books without the leaſt Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are recommended by thoſe five Miniſters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The next thing therefore to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is, what thoſe five Miniſters have recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As to the former part of their Vindication, I leave the particulars thereof (if any think them worth their Notice) to ſuch as are or may be more properly concerned with it: And as to the latter part of it, which had alſo the approbation of the aforeſaid five Miniſters, this relating to me I have ſaid ſomething in anſwer to it before, and therefore I ſhall now proceed to confute Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s practice of ſinging from their own Confeſſions, collected from both the Parts of his Vindication: As in <hi>page</hi> 59. he ſays, on <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. and <hi>Mark</hi> 14.26. <q>That tho' this be true, that this word <hi>Hymneo</hi> be not limitted only to Songs of Praiſe, it will not prove (ſaith he) what this Author affirms, that it is properly uſed, or ſignifies ſimply to praiſe. And in <hi>page</hi> 69. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays thus, I bring not theſe Teſtimonies (<hi>viz. James</hi> 5.13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.) to prove conjoynt Singing of the whole Congregation together, but only to prove that ſinging of Pſalms is the Duty of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: The lawfulneſs of conjoynt finging I argue from other Scripture Grounds in my Eſſay. And in <hi>page</hi> 12, 13. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays, as to ſinging with the conjoin'd voices of many together, I only plead for the lawfulneſs and warrantableneſs of it, which I prove from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Scripture Arguments. — Not but that I allow, that 'tis alſo lawful for one voice
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175969:7"/>alone to ſing the praiſes of God. Indeed in a publick Aſſembly I conclude 'tis much more warrantable for the whole Congregation to ſing with conjoyn'd voices than for one Perſon there to ſing by himſelf, becauſe we have ſeveral unexceptionable Inſtances in Scripture for the former, but none (as I know of) of the latter: And therefore ſeeing Singing either ſingly or conjointly are but different Circumſtances of performing the ſame thing, I appeal (ſaith he) to every impartial Reader, whether I ought not (as I did) to conſider, whether ſinging the praiſes of God be at all a Chriſtian Duty, before I diſcourſe of theſe or any other Circumſtances of it. And much more is it unreaſonable, that he ſhould oblige me to prove, that 'tis no leſs than a Chriſtian Duty to ſing in Metre or Rhime, and with artificial Tunes, which are but accidental modes of ſinging, and not eſſential to it. And ſo far am I (ſaith he) from aſſerting it to be a Chriſtian Duty, in this particular mode of it, that I expreſly declare it wholly indifferent, to ſing the Divine Praiſes either in Proſe, or Metre or Rhime, according as we judge moſt for Edification. Indeed I give my opinion for the preference of the latter before the former, as more eaſie to be performed in a harmonious and regular manner, and therefore more generally practiſed by the proteſtants than ſinging in proſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And in like manner (ſays Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>) I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning ſinging by artificial Tunes, not aſſerting or believing them eſſential to the Performance of this Duty, but only requiſite for the more regular performance of it.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:175969:7"/>
            <p>
               <q>And in <hi>page</hi> 82. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> further ſays, That whatſoever becomes of theſe accidental Modes of Metre, Rhime, and Artificial Tunes, 'tis ſinging the Divine Praiſes it ſelf, in a proper ſence, <hi>viz.</hi> vocally, that I aſſert to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duty, which Duty may be performed (tho' I think, with the generallity of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, not ſo well) without theſe modes, as well as a Perſon may be rightly baptized after another manner than with his Face upward. And in <hi>page</hi> 81. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays, The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence I have ſhewn to be between the parts of Divine Worſhip, and the accidental modes and ways of its performance. And he alſo tells us, that the Holy Scriptures is to be our only Rule in Divine Worſhip, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, 1. For all the eſſential parts of Divine Worſhip we muſt have an expreſs Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the word. And, 2. All the accidental Modes and Circumſtances of Divine Worſhip muſt be ordered ſuitable to the general Rules thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo as may be moſt for Order and Edification, as he ſaith in the foregoing part of the ſame page, that Chriſtian Churches have liberty to order ſuch accidental modes and circumſtances of Divine Worſhip as are not particularly preſcribed in the Word, as they ſhall judge moſt for Edification. And in <hi>page</hi> 47. ſpeaking of external modes and circumſtances of Worſhip, which (ſaith he) I take to be in the power of the major part of a Church, ſo far as to warrant their own practice therein.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Having made the preceeding Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s words, recommended and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175969:8"/>approved by the foreſaid five Miniſters, I ſhall make Obſervations on them as follows. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſeeing Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.30. and <hi>Mark</hi> 14.26. confeſſeth, that the Greek word <hi>Hymneo,</hi> which in our laſt Bibles is there Tranſlated to ſing an Hymn, is not limitted in its ſignification only to Songs of Praiſe, then ſurely conſidering alſo that the ſame Bibles render the ſame word <hi>Hymneo,</hi> and <hi>Tehillah</hi> in the Old Teſtament, ſimply to praiſe, notwithſtanding the ſtir he makes about it, he cannot from his own Confeſſions prove from thoſe Texts that Chriſt and his Diſciples ſung the Hymn or Praiſe after Supper, nor that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> ſang their praiſe, for 'tis the ſame Greek word, <hi>Hymneo,</hi> that is there alſo uſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>page</hi> 69. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays, That he does not prove conjoynt ſinging from <hi>James</hi> 5.13. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.16. but only that ſinging of Pſalms is a Duty: So that their own Pens having owned ſo much of the inſufficiency of thoſe Texts of Scripture to prove their way of Singing, I think we may fairly conclude from their own Confeſſions, that it cannot be a Goſpel-Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> plainly diſtinguiſheth and makes a difference between the Eſſential parts of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, and the Accidental Modes and Circumſtances thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He ſays, That for all the Eſſential parts of Divine Worſhip we muſt have an expreſs Preſcription in the Word: But that all the Accidental Modes and Circumſtances thereof which he diſtinguiſheth, and makes no Eſſentials of Divine Worſhip, theſe he ſaith are left to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175969:8"/>the liberty, and he takes to be in the power of the major part of a Church to warrant their own Practice therein.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> tells us what thoſe accidental modes and circumſtances of ſinging are, that are no eſſential parts thereof, nor of Divine Worſhip. And, 1. He ſays, that the conjoin'd ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a publick Aſſembly, or of a whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, is but a circumſtance, and that he only pleads for the lawfulneſs and warrantableneſs of it. Obſerve it well, he only pleads ſo for it as he ſays, from ſeveral Scriptural Inſtances, which to reconcile his Diſcourſe fairly together, muſt imply that he does not plead for ſinging with conjoyn'd voices as an abſolute Duty, from any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs preſcription in the Word of God, but as a lawful Circumſtance from ſome (pretended) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and ſo he makes his conjoyn'd voices but an accidental Circumſtance of ſinging, and no eſſential part of Divine Worſhip. 2. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> aſſerts, that ſinging in Metre and Rhime is no eſſential part thereof. And, 3. That ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with artificial tunes are but accidental modes of ſinging, and not eſſential to it, nor to Divine Worſhip. 4. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays, that ſinging the Divine Praiſes it ſelf may be performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe modes, <hi>viz.</hi> of Metre, Rhime, and Artificial Tunes, and I may fairly add without their ſinging with conjoyn'd voices, it being as he ſays but a circumſtance of ſinging, and ſo alſo as I have ſhewed 'tis no eſſential of it, nor of Divine Worſhip: So that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> and his five Commendators, <hi>viz. Joſeph Maiſters, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Collins, Joſeph Stennet, John Piggot</hi> and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Harriſon,</hi> having expreſly owned and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175969:9"/>publickly in print, that ſinging with conjoyn'd voices is but a circumſtance of ſinging-worſhip, which they themſelves ſhew is no eſſential part thereof, and that ſinging in Metre and Rhime, and alſo by Artificial Tunes, are all but accidental modes of Divine Worſhip, and no eſſential parts thereof; it is all one as to ſay, (except their preſtinted forms of words and matter) that their whole external mode, manner, way and practice of ſinging, is no eſſential part of Divine Worſhip; and herein I agree with them, and ſo (except their preſtinted form of words) they have joyned iſſue with me, to bring this Controverſie of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to an end, and to a ſingle point, <hi>viz.</hi> That a Chriſtian Church has liberty to order ſuch accidental modes and circumſtances of Divine Worſhip as are not particularly preſcribed in the Word of God, as ſhe ſhall judge moſt for Ediſication.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Controverſie of Singing being now reduced from Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s and his five Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dators Confeſſions to this ſingle point, and they having ſhewed and aſſerted their ſinging with conjoyn'd voces, in Metre and Rhime, by Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Tunes, to be but accidental modes and circumſtances of Worſhip, that differ from the eſſential parts thereof, ſo as that for all the eſſential parts of it we muſt have an expreſs preſcription in the Word, and that all the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental modes and circumſtances of it are leſt to the Liberty of a Church, it conſequently implies, that all their aforeſaid accidental modes and circumſtances, or ways of ſinging, have no preſcription in the Holy Scriptures. And ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we ſhould grant them (as he aſſerts them)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175969:9"/>to be no Eſſentials of his Singing-worſhip, yet I cannot conceive what his Cauſe will gain by it; for whatever Name he gives them, and flut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he makes, as if he had ſome Scripture-ground for his conjoint-ſinging, more than for his artificial Tunes, Rhime and Metre, yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he makes it but a circumſtance, and all of them accidental modes and circumſtances, that are left to the Liberty of a Church, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that none of them are preſcribed in the Word of God, I cannot ſee but that they are of the ſame nature, as all the ſuperſtitious modes and circumſtances of Worſhip of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are, and ſo Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> has ſtill no better warrant for his practiſe of ſinging than the Papiſts have for all their Trumpery, which according to his Doctrine before recited, the <hi>major</hi> part of his Church has Liberty and Power to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant their practice of: So that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s, and his five Commendators Popiſh principle, tends to the ruine of ours, and the Proteſtants Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation more in general.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I ſhall demonſtrate, That altho' Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> aſſerts his unſcriptural, accidental modes and circumſtances of ſinging, to be no eſſential parts thereof, and I agree with him, that they they are no eſſentials (nor any parts) of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, yet I do not agree with him that they are no eſſential parts of his ſinging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, becauſe he uſeth his artificial Tunes and conjoint vocal ſinging, as ſuch modes and circumſtances of it, that without them he cannot perform his ſinging Church-worſhip, and therefore they are eſſentials of it; for that which is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to any thing, is that which ſo belongs to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175969:10"/>being of it, that without it it cannot compleatly be, which I ſhall explain more particularly. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That his ſinging with conjoined voices is an eſſential part of his ſtanding Church-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is plain, becauſe without this mode of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd voices his Ordinance ceaſeth, and he muſt either bring into the Church the practice of ſinging with a ſingle voice, or no proper, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, melodious ſinging at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tho' he calls his artificial tunes accidental modes of ſinging, yet they are eſſentials of his ſinging, becauſe he cannot perform his Singing-Worſhip with conjoin'd voices without ſuch Tunes. Indeed he tells us, That that Singing it ſelf which he aſſerts to be a Chriſtian Duty, may be performed without ſuch tunes, <hi>pag.</hi> 82. but what kind of ſinging he there means, which is not his practice by artificial Tunes, he yet conceals from us. As for Tunes immediately inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt, he pretends not to them, and as for natural Tunes they may ſerve to make a natural noiſe, enough to fright away natural men, rather than to gain their affections to his Worſhip.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His ſinging in Rhyme and Metre he calls an indifferent thing, and alſo accidental modes of Worſhip; but tho' he terms them ſo, or does ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them indifferent Circumſtances, yet he does not uſe them in his church, as accidental or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial parts of a common civil action, as ſuch, but of his Divine Worſhip, and therefore whatever he calls them, they are eſſentials of it, for there are no circumſtances of worſhip but what are eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to the compleat performance of it. It's true, there are Circumſtances attending Worſhip that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175969:10"/>are not of Worſhip, but of actions meerly as ſuch, as one particular fixed hour of the day for Chriſtians to meet together does attend the time and place of their Worſhip, but one particular prefixed hour is but a circumſtance of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of meeting as ſuch, and ſo no eſſential cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of Worſhip, as time and place is, for another hour may ſerve as well, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the circumſtances of time and place the Worſhip it ſelf cannot be. And notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> tells us plainly, that artificial Tunes, Metre and Rhime, are not eſſential to ſinging, yet I perceive that he himſelf in effect makes them eſſential to it: For he ſays, that 'tis his Opinion, that to ſing in Rhime and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre is more eaſie to be performed in an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious and regular manner than in proſe, and that ſinging in artificial tunes is requiſite for the more regular performance of it. Now is not that which is requiſite for the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular performing of that Worſhip eſſential to it, ſeeing it is not ſo regular without it? Surely, if artificial Tunes, Rhime and Metre, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Rule, or make his Rule of Singing, whatever it be more perfect for that Worſhip, they muſt needs belong unto it, and be eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to the more compleat performance of it, than without thoſe modes and circumſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> To me it ſeemeth plain, that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s terms of accidental modes and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are only to gild over his Error, that our People may the eaſier ſwallow it down, and how much he writes after the Copy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the preface to the Book of Common-Prayer, appears from the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175969:11"/>Citation out of it: For it's there ſaid, <q>That the particular forms of Divine Worſhip, and the Rites and Ceremonies appointed to be uſed therein, being things in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture indifferent and alterable, and ſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, it is but reaſonable that upon weighty and important Conſiderations, according to the various exigency of Times, and Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſuch Changes and Alterations ſhould be made therein, as to thoſe that are in place of Authority, ſhould from time to time ſeem ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary or expedient.</q> And concerning their Ceremonies that have had their beginning by the Inſtitution of Man, 'tis there further ſaid, <q>That thoſe that remain are retained for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Order, which (upon juſt cauſes) may be altered and changed, and therefore are not to be eſteemed equal with God's Law.</q> From whence I Obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That as tis 'ſaid the particular Forms of the Service of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are things in their own nature indifferent and alterable, ſo Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> makes his ſinging in Rhime and Metre, and by artificial Tunes, but indifferent things, that are alterable; for he ſays, that ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divine Praiſes may be performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, as well as a Perſon may be rightly baptized after another manner than with his face upward, <hi>pag.</hi> 13, &amp; 82.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That as the Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> originally inſtituted by Man, are for Diſcipline and Order, ſo Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays, That all the accidental Modes and Circumſtances of Divine Worſhip muſt be ordered ſuitable to the general Rules thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> (ſaith he) ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175969:11"/>as may be moſt for Order and Edification, <hi>page</hi> 81.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are not to be eſteemed equal with God's Law, ſo Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> calls his ways of ſinging in rhime and metre, and by artificial tunes [with conjoin'd voices] but accidental modes, and [circumſtances] that he aſſerts are not equal with the eſſential parts of Divine Worſhip pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Word of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſame Scripture that is uſed in the preface to the Book of Common-prayer for their Ceremonies, is uſed in Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Eſſay, <hi>page</hi> 88. for his mode of ſinging in artificial tunes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order;</hi> which to underſtand otherwiſe than of the Order and Decency preſcribed in the Word, and before laid down in the Rule of Worſhip, in the ſame Chapter, is a Subverſion of the Word of God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I may alſo add, That as the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> did formerly preſs their Forms and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Worſhip, under the Notion of indifferent things, upon the Conſciences of the Diſſenters, who by no means could be made to ſwallow them down, tho' gilded over with their Terms; ſo tho' Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> has declared againſt impoſing of his accidental modes and circumſtances of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, yet he and his Companions have ſo far fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the former ſteps of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as to preſs their modes and circumſtances, which they own are no eſſential parts of Goſpel-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſo hard upon our Churches, as to occaſion many Troubles and Diſtractions among us. So that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> and his five Companions agree ſo well with the Preface to the Book of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayer,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:175969:12"/>about the nature of humane modes and circumſtances of Worſhip, that we have reaſon to believe they have learnt their Notions from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whereby they are infecting our Churches with ſuch Principles as will natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally lead them to conform at leaſt to their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> I ſhall take ſome Notice of what Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> refers us to in <hi>page</hi> 81. Where he tells us, that he has ſhewn the Difference between the parts of Divine Worſhip, and the accidental modes and ways of its performance, in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going — <hi>page</hi> 15. And in <hi>page</hi> 47. ſpeaking of thoſe accidental modes and circumſtances of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip as are not particularly preſcribed in the Word, he ſays, <hi>That there are many ſuch, every one muſt needs know, whereof ſome inſtances</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have been given,</hi> pag. 15. where I find Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> mentioneth the three following particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He there ſaith, <q>For a Man to provide for his Family all I preſume (ſaith he) will grant to be a Chriſtian, yea, a Moral Duty, but 'tis at the Liberty of every man's choice in what juſt way he doth it, whether by the uſe of this or the other Art or Trade.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> What is this to our caſe of Divine Worſhip? becauſe every man has liberty to chooſe and uſe what lawful Art or Trade he pleaſeth, for the maintenance of his Family, therefore muſt Chriſtians have ſo great a Liberty to chooſe and practiſe what accidental modes and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Worſhip they pleaſe? If this be granted, then if our Churches pleaſe they may practice not only common Singing, but the Common Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> Common-Prayer,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175969:12"/>Common Baptiſm, or Sprinkling of Infants, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Goſſips to Anſwer for them, Kneeling at the Altar, and at Confeſſion and Abſolution, Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Eaſt and Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and may ſet up Organs for their Publik Worſhip, and a heap of other Ceremonies that were never appointed by Jeſus Chriſt, but accidentally happened from the Errors and Inventions of Men, who do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by virtually deny that Chriſt has left his Goſpel-Church compleat Directions in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He there faith, in <hi>pag.</hi> 15. <q>'Tis the Duty of Miniſters to Preach the Goſpel, for the Converſion of Sinners, and the Edification of Believers; but none (ſaith he) I ſuppoſe will affirm it is ſo, to preach it in this or the other particular way or method.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Having publiſh'd my mind concerning Preaching, in my <hi>Reply to Mr.</hi> Benjamin Keach<hi>'s Breach Repair'd,</hi> pag. 75, 76. &amp; 119, to 123. and it being too large to recite here, I ſhall refer my Reader thither for further Satisfaction, if it be deſired, and only here ſay, That though I greatly diſapprove of Pre-ſtinted Forms of Words in Preaching, yet there is ſome difference in Scripture between the caſe of Preaching and modes of Praiſes or Prayer. However, it is not at the liberty of preachers to unite their Voices together in that Service; and if any argue for a Pre-ſtinted Form of Preaching, it is no Example for a liberty of modes, or for a Pre-ſtinted Form of Singing: If it be, Why not for a Pre-ſtinted Form of Prayer alſo, which they may equally bring it for? And till they anſwer me this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, there is no need of any other. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:175969:13"/>1.13. &amp; 2.15. and 4.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. and 4.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13, 15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> in the ſame page, ſays of Water-Baptiſm, <q>That the Dipping of Believers, is Eſſential to it, but there are (ſaith he) dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent accidental modes wherein it may be adminiſtred, which are at the liberty of the Adminiſtrator to chooſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are no modes nor circumſtances of that Ordinance but what are Eſſential to the right and compleat performance of it, for ſuch modes and circumſtances that are left to the liberty of the Adminiſtrator, <hi>viz.</hi> whether to Dip the Perſon with his Face upward or down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, are no modes nor circumſtances of or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Ordinance it ſelf, becauſe the compleat performance of it is not tyed to the uſe of either of them; and therefore, though the Adminiſtrator has liberty to make them modes and circumſtances of the Action of Dipping, yet not as of or Eſſentially belonging to that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, becauſe neither of them are preſcribed in the Word, and that Ordinance may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without any one, or either of thoſe modes and circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Thus I have diſcovered the Weakneſs of Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Arguments, or Inſtances to juſtifie his accidental modes and circumſtances of Singing, to be left to the liberty of a Church; which No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in my Opinion, his own Pen does alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and clearly overthrow; for in <hi>pag.</hi> 58. he aſſerts, <q>That though the Light of Nature be ſufficient (if duly attended to) to teach us, that we ought to uſe all our Faculties for the Glory of our Creator and Benefactor;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175969:13"/>yet I count it not ſo perfect a Guide as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently to inſtruct us what peculiar faculties we ſhould exert in ſtated Church-worſhip, or how we ſhould uſe them therein, without the more perfect Guidance of the Word.</q> Now if this be true, as I firmly believe it is, then ſurely to leave to the Liberty of a Church, according as Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays, to warrant the practice of his unſcriptural and accidental modes and circumſtances, and conſequently his practice of ſinging, which from his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions is ſhewed to be no eſſential part of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, is to leave a meer humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention to the Liberty of the inſufficient Guide of the Light within, to be warranted and uſed for Goſpel-Worſhip. But as our Saviour ſaith, That <hi>In vain they do worſhip me, teaching for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines the Commandments of Men,</hi> Mat. 15.9. So the Reformation from Popery brake forth, and was maintained by the Light and Authority of the Holy Scriptures, which the Faithful Saints and Martyrs of Chriſt embraced, in oppoſition to all the Ceremonies and Inventions of Men, rejecting all things in the Worſhip of God and Adminiſtrations of Goſpel-Ordinances, which they believed were not preſcribed in his Word, as hath been particularly ſhewed in my laſt Treatiſe. Beſides, we have the Teſtimony of the Servants of Chriſt in this laſt age, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in their Printed Confeſſions of Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Presbyterians, Independants, and Baptiſts Confeſſions of Faith, (to which laſt is Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Collins</hi>'s Name) where in <hi>Article</hi> 21, 22. they ſay, <q>That the acceptable way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the true God, is inſtituted by himſelf,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175969:14"/>and ſo limited by (or to) his own revealed Will, that he may not be worſhipped according to the Imaginations and Devices of Men, or the Suggeſtion of Satan, under any viſible Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, (mark the following words) or any other way not preſcribed in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Which in <hi>Article</hi> 1. they ſay, are the Supream Judge, by which all Controverſies of Religion are to be determined.</q> So that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Principle of the Liberty and Power of a Goſpel-Church, to order and warrant their own practice of unpreſcribed modes of Divine Worſhip as ſhe pleaſes, does ſtrike at a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation-principle of ours, and the Proteſtants Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation more in general.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> I deſire it may be duely conſidered, how our ſinging Brethren are driven from refuge to refuge, and at laſt have had their Practice of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clearly confuted from their own Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: For thoſe Elders and Miniſters whoſe Names are ſet to the <hi>Reply</hi> to Mr. <hi>Robert Steed</hi>'s Epiſtle, among whom are ſet the Names of ſome of our aforeſaid Miniſters, <hi>viz. Joſeph Maiſters, William Collins,</hi> and alſo <hi>R. Allen,</hi> in <hi>page</hi> 8. they ſay, <q>That ſuch was the Singing of God's People under the Law, (<hi>viz.</hi> with voices lift up together) and the Churches are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to ſing Pſalms in the New Teſtament, and no other way preſcribed or laid down how they ſhould ſing. <hi>Ergo,</hi> (ſay they) the Churches are now to ſing in the times of the Goſpel, as God's People under the Law. And they farther ſay, in <hi>page</hi> 24. That tho' Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and Singing-men ceaſed when Chriſt came, yet ſinging did not ceaſe, — becauſe (ſay they)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175969:14"/>it is part of Moral and Natural Religion, and therefore a ſtanding Ordinance.</q> From whence we may Obſerve, That notwithſtanding the ſtir they have made about the Singing we find in the New Teſtament, and of Chriſt and his Diſciples, and of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> ſinging together, yet we may plainly ſee from their own Words, that they do not relye upon Goſpel-Evidence as ſufficient, to juſtifie their way of ſinging; and finding no countenance for their Practice, from any Example or Inſtitution under the Law, they flee for help to their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Light within, to make their Singing a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ordinance. And tho' Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> and his five Commendators, in their <hi>Eſſay</hi> and <hi>Vindication</hi> of it, make a flutter, as if they had found ſomething in the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> for their ſinging with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd Voices, (which I have ſhewed proves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it) yet they ſtill ſtick to the inſufficient Guide of the Light within, the major part of a Church, as their warrant for the prectice of it. So that if we conſider their way of ſinging with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd voices, artificial tunes, and rhime, and metre, which they own are not preſcribed in the New Teſtament, and as Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſhews are no eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial parts of ſinging, and ſo no parts at all of Divine Worſhip, it cannot from their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions be a Goſpel-Ordinance, becauſe they own 'tis neither contained in the New Teſtament, nor is any part of Goſpel-worſhip. And therefore I hope Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> and his five Companions (with the reſt of our Singing Brethren) will neither plead for it, nor practice it any longer, ſeeing they have no better Warrant for that Worſhip than the inſufficient Guide of the Light within,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175969:15"/>the major part of a Goſpel-Church, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than what may be ſaid for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Humane Inventions more.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeeing their own Pens has thus overthrown the whole of their way of ſinging, (except their preſtinted Form of Words, and this alſo until they have found ſome other tune to ſing them by than what are artificial) and that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> ſays in <hi>page</hi> 82. in diſtinctinction to his accidental modes of Singing, that 'tis ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divine Praiſes it ſelf (which he there ſays may be done without thoſe Modes) in a proper Senſe, <hi>viz.</hi> vocally, that he aſſerts to be a Chriſtian Duty; if he and his Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors will ſtand by theſe their plain Confeſſions and Aſſertions, I hope our Controverſie is not only brought to an End, but alſo will be quickly ended. For we reject as no Eſſentials of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, all that they would have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they have ſo rejected, as before is ſhewed: And we do aſſert, Singing the Divine Praiſes it ſelf in a proper ſenſe to be a Chriſtian Duty, but depending on an extraordinary Gift (or Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Enrichings of the Word and Spirit) as other extraordinary ways of delivering the Word of God in the Apoſtles time, with ſtrange Tongues and Interpretations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did, and ſo all the difference between them and us, ſo far as I can ſee at preſent, is, That they aſſert Singing preſtinted forms of Praiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be a Duty, and at preſent are ſo far in the dark how it ſhould be performed, as effectually to tell us, that their manner, ways and practice of Singing, is not preſcribed in the Word of God, but that it is at the Liberty, and in the power of a Church to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:175969:15"/>warrant their own practice thereof as they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>But we ſay, That that Rule of Goſpel-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15, 16, 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which they ſubject unto for other parts of Divine Worſhip mentioned with the Pſalm, as alike pertaining to it, tho' they will not ſing by it, with a ſingle voice: This, we ſay, gives as clear Directions how, and in what mode or manner Singing ſhould be perform'd in a Goſpel-Church, as for the delivering other Gifts of the Holy Splrit. Beſides, we are not in the dark about it, as they are, but can, and have already, again and again clearly ſhewed them from the Light of the New Teſtament, that both the matter and the melody of Goſpel-Singing was as the Spirit gave them utterance, and it was a kind of Duty exhorted unto, as the Saints were exhorted to covet after other extraordinary Gifts of the Holy Spirit, and ſo was not commanded as an abſolute con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Ordinance, but as a Circumſtantial and Additional Duty to the great Ordinance of Thankſgiving and Praiſing of God, and of Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Admoniſhing, which were performed by the extraordinary Gifts of the Holy Spirit, which Ordinances themſelves ſtill remain to be Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and are to be performed in an ordinary miniſtration, without the additional mode of Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, while we have not ſuch an Additional Gift as the Primitive Chriſtians had, till God may pleaſe to adorn his Worſhip again with it, by a freſh effuſion of his Holy Spirit, and then Singing will be a Duty to thoſe that are quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for it, and for all to ſeek after, as after the perfection of Gifts and Graces for Private and Publick Worſhip.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:175969:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> To conclude on the aforeſaid mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Seeing our Antagoniſts are in Effect, Summ and Subſtance, brought to theſe Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is no way preſcribed or laid down in the New Teſtament how they ſhould ſing, <hi>i. e.</hi> for their manner of Singing with conjoyn'd Voices, Artificial Tunes, and Rhime, and Metre, and that they have no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Warrant in the Scripture, nor from the Natural Light within, to make thoſe modes of Singing which are practiſed as Divine Worſhip, any Eſſential Parts thereof.</p>
            <p>I propoſe it to the Judgment of all Sober and Judicious Chriſtians, whether their Confeſſions do not clearly demonſtrate they are convinced in their Conſciences, that their practice of Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a meer Humane Invention? and whether if Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> or any of his five Commendators do either practice it, or open their mouths for it, as a Goſpel Ordinance or a Chriſtian Duty, they may not be fairly charged from the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their own Pens with Will-worſhip, or to act or ſpeak againſt the Light of their own Conſciences? And if they trouble our Churches further with it, and their Popiſh Principle of the Liberty and Power of a Goſpel Church, on which they ground their Warrant for their way of Singing, whether there will not be reaſon at leaſt to ſuſpect, that for ſome outward Intereſt more than for Conſcience ſake, they are turning Adverſaries againſt the true Intereſt of the Baptiſts Churches, and wilful Betrayers of our Reformation, and are laying the Foundation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us of a grand Apoſtacy in Divine Worſhip? And conſidering that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> and his five Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175969:16"/>in Defence of their Singing Worſhip, have given us Ground to fear they deſign to alter our Churches Settlement, and to new model them; and ſeeing the Light and Power of Truth has forced their own Pens to crumble their cauſe to nothing, or to ſuch a point as may be fairly drawn from their own Confeſſions and Practice, which they have cauſe to be aſhamed of, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe accidental modes and circumſtances of ſinging, and many others that are not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly preſcribed in the Word of God, and (as they ſay) are no Eſſential Parts thereof, nor of Divine Worſhip, are left to the Liberty of the Inſufficient Guide of the Light within, the <hi>major</hi> part of a Goſpel-Church, to warrant their own Practice of, as Divine Worſhip, or as Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Parts thereof, ſo as ſhe ſhall judge moſt for Edification. I hope therefore 'tis a ſeaſonable Requeſt, that they will at laſt ſhew themſelves to be ſuch good Chriſtians, and real Friends to that Foundation-Principle which they have ſtruck at, as before is ſhewed, of the Proteſtants Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in general, and to the Baptized Churches in particular, as under a due Senſe of the wrong they have done our Profeſſion, and the ſhame they have brought upon it, to labour to heal their wounds, to confirm the minds of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren whom they have ſhaken, and to ſatisfie all that are concerned, with ſincere Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Errors, and Hearty Aſſurances that hereafter they will joyn with their Brethren againſt all Innovations in Goſpel-worſhip, and Defilements of Humane Inventions whatſoever: And in ſo doing, our Churches will have cauſe to give thanks to God for their Recovery. And
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175969:17"/>their Objection againſt my preſent being no Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of any Church, (the occaſion whereof is ſo well known, as that they do not, neither can they juſtly blame me for it) I hope will quickly be removed, for excepting ſome of them (whoſe Churches differ in Profeſſion, and are not in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the reſt of their Churches as I know of) 'tis they and other Singers that have ſo mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the Communion of their Churches, that I cannot with Satisfaction of Conſcience joyn my ſelf to any of them until I ſee a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The foregoing matters being concluded, I ſhall now proceed to anſwer Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, at the end of Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Vindication of his <hi>Eſſay:</hi> But before I treat thereof, I ſhall here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, That the practice of ſinging with united voices of Men and Women, Profeſſors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, in the Worſhip of God, in his Goſpel-Church, being firſt preached up, and vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſt upon us by ſeveral of our Brethren, and aſſerted in Print to the view of all men, I thought it neceſſary for the preſervation of the Peace and Purity of the Baptized Churches, to preſent them with ſome Arguments againſt that way of Worſhip; which notwithſtanding they were offered in a Chriſtian manner, and were conſonant to the Principles of our Churches, yet ſeveral of our Singers have appeared in print againſt me, in ſuch a ſubtil Spirit of Injuſtice, Deceit and Lying, as hath coſt me much Labour, Time and Money, out of my own private Purſe to maintain the Truth and Common Cauſe and Intereſt of our Churches, from being cruſh'd by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175969:17"/>them, an Account whereof has been already given in Print, ſo far as hath been thought ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to anſwer the Calls of Providence, and to clear my Books from thoſe falſe Repreſentations of my Principles about Singing, groſs Abuſes and foul Untruths publiſhed in Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s <hi>Breach Repaired,</hi> and other Pamphlets, in wrong to me and my Printed Treatiſes; which Abuſes being juſtly charged upon him and them in Print, many of them under the Hands of ſeveral Paſtors of Churches, and ſeveral particular things by nine other Brethren, they ſtill remain unanſwered, on ſo clear a Record, as that they have not ſince in more than four years time appear'd in vindication of themſelves: And the reaſon why they have not done it may eaſily be perceived, for the matter charg'd upon them is in their own Books, and ſo cannot be ſtifled from the knowledge of any that will take the Trouble to look into it. But to proceed, my chief Buſineſs being to give an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi>'s Defence, and to clear my ſelf from his Slander, I ſhall here recite Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Words, which are the ground of my Charge againſt him, and are as follows: Saith he,</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Author which Mr. <hi>M.</hi> cites out of <hi>Marlorate</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. pretends it is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with what words they praiſed God; that is, whether it was with the common Paſſover Hymn, or ſome other of Chriſts own, which might be more ſuitable to the occaſion, and whether they ſaug this Praiſe, or ſpake it ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; the following Words of the Author not being well rendred by Mr. <hi>Timme,</hi> I ſhall ſet down, they are theſe, <hi>Graecum verbum laudem
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175969:18"/>quidem, maxime quae Deo debetur; includit, non autem neceſſario evincit, quòd cecinerint;</hi> i. e. <hi>The</hi> Greek <hi>Word indeed includes praiſe, chiefly that which is due to God, but undoubtedly it doth evince that they ſang.</hi> 1. From the genuine ſignification of the Original Word. And, 2. From the Current of Learned men, who go this way.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Latine was falſly Engliſhed, for it ſhould be as it was afterwards altered by them in a few of thoſe Books, <hi>but it doth [not] ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily evince that they ſang;</hi> which is the ſame in ſence as my Author Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> reads it, <hi>viz. but it doth not thereupon follow that they did ſing it.</hi> Now as to the Correction that was made (after this Abuſe was taken notice of abroad) the whole Paragraph was not taken away, as it ought to have been, neither was the former part of it at all altered, which diſcovers the Deſign of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> to deceive his unlearned Reader with a falſe Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Latine, as plainly appears from the Paragraph. 1. Becauſe for Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> to tell us, that Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> had not well rendred <hi>Marlorate</hi>'s Latine, when he had rendred his true ſence, he muſt needs do it on purpoſe to deceive his unlearned Reader with his falſe tranſlation of it; for otherwiſe ſeeing Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> had done it in the right ſence, there was no need at all for Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> to write that Paragraph againſt him. 2. If the word [not] had only been left out in Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Engliſh, we might have imputed it to be the Printers fault; but we alſo find that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> ſaith, that Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> pretended it is uncertain, whether they ſang that Praiſe, or ſpake it ſimply, and then in contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175969:18"/>to him, he aſſerts, <hi>That undoubtedly it doth evince that they ſang.</hi> 3. 'Tis plain that the word [not] was left out, on purpoſe to deceive the unlearned Reader, becauſe there is no Reaſon to believe, that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> did deſign poſitively to affirm from <hi>Marlorate</hi>'s Latine, That Chriſt and his Diſciples did not ſing the Hymn after Supper, by tranſlating the Latine falſly, to give an undoubted Teſtimony againſt his own Cauſe, but to make his unlearned Reader believe that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly they did ſing, when he knew in his Conſcience that the Latine leaves it undetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſaying only, <hi>That it doth not neceſſarily evince or ſhew that they ſang,</hi> Mat. 26.30.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I well remember, that I told Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> between him and me alone, of his abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my Author, and he excuſed it with laying the fault upon the Printer; but I anſwered, that tho' Printers ſometimes correct Words, yet they never uſe to add a whole Paragraph to their Authors Books; and therefore I ſaid, it look'd like a deſign'd Abuſe, to which he made me no anſwer, and ſo we parted.</p>
            <p>And as to the Correction that was made in ſome few of thoſe Books, to cover the Deceit from me at firſt, it was not of the former part of the Paragraph, for the alteration began at the laſt Clauſe of the Engliſhing the Latine. And I have yet reaſon to complain, that it was no ſufficient ſatisfaction for the wrong done me, becauſe ſome time after it was told me that this Abuſe was corrected, I deſired my Brother Mr. <hi>Luke Leader</hi> to go to Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> for one of them, and my Brother teſtifies that Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> took down ſeveral of thoſe Books from off the Shelf,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175969:19"/>before he could find one that was corrected; and to my own knowledge ſince it was pretended they were corrected, ſome of thoſe Books were in other places expoſed to publick ſale uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. Beſides, I have alſo ſeen, and can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce two others of thoſe Books, that are teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to be lately bought at Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s, or of his Daughters, that ſold them in their Shop in the months of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July</hi> laſt, 1696. that have this abuſe remaining in them uncorrected, in the laſt leaf of the Book, which might eaſily have been removed if they would. Having thus recited the matter of Fact, tho' not in the ſame Order as it was printed before, I ſhall here take ſome notice of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Defence that he makes for himſelf, at the end of Mr. <hi>Alllen</hi>'s Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his <hi>Eſſay.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I Obſerve, that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> owns that he wrote that ſheet of Paper, <hi>viz.</hi> at the end of Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s <hi>Breach repaired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He acknowledgeth there was a falſe Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of a Latine Paſſage in it, but ſays, that this was done by the Overſeer of the Preſs, who altered the truth of his Tranſlation: And by this he alſo owns himſelf to be the Author of that Paragraph, the former part whereof, which proves that he deſign'd to make that falſe Tranſlation, he makes no Anſwer to.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He tells us that he ſtrictly enjoined the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Book, (<hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach</hi>) that the leaf wherein it was ſhould be reprinted, and that a Letter was immediately ſent to me, to let me know that this falſe Tranſlation was not in his Copy; and yet notwithſtanding this that I falſly in Print charge him with this Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175969:19"/>And he alſo ſays, that this willful Sin he laid to my Charge, before an Aſſembly of Elders and Meſſengers at <hi>Devonſhire-Square</hi> Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Houſe ſome years ago, where being Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, (as he ſaith) I had, to the beſt of his remembrance, nothing to ſay in my own Defence. This being the Sence and Subſtance of Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi>'s Defence, my Anſwer follows. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To what he ſays of a Letter being ſent me, I muſt return him this Anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> That I have not the leaſt knowledge of any ſuch Letter that was ever ſent me, or came to my Hands, from him or any other Perſon whatſoever, concerning that matter: But if it had been ſo, yet his Evidence in this caſe had been no better than what he has now preſented to us in print, and is diſproved by the former part of his own Paragraph, which is as clear a Teſtimony, as if there had been an hundred perſonal Witneſſes againſt him: And therefore, the main part of his Defence, which is that he corrected the Engliſh, and added the word [not] which was left out, does not at all clear him from my charge, ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the former part of his Paragraph, <hi>viz.</hi> That he wrote it, and conſequently did falſly Engliſh that Latine, on purpoſe to abuſe my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and deprive his unlearned Reader of that ſound Teſtimony of the true ſignification of the <hi>Greek</hi> Word <hi>Hymneo,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. In the next place my buſineſs is to clear my ſelf from the latter part of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Defence, where he ſays, that this willful Sin (<hi>viz.</hi> of charging him with this falſe Tranſlation) he laid to my Charge before an Aſſembly of Elders and Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175969:20"/>at <hi>Devonſhire-ſquare</hi> Meeting-Houſe, ſome years ago; where being ſelf-condemned, as he ſaith, I had, to the beſt of his Remembrance, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay in my own Defence. To which I Anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That that Aſſembly of Elders and Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers at <hi>Devonſhire-ſquare</hi> Meeting-Houſe, which Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> ſpeaks of, was in the Year 1692. and was the firſt time that ſuch a general Aſſembly met in that place, that ever I heard of, or was concerned with, and ſince that I have not been preſent at any ſuch Aſſembly; and therefore what Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> aſſerts concerning my ſelf-condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cannot relate to any other time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Through the unrighteous Clamour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> and Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach,</hi> with the help of ſome of their Friends, the Names of my two Books, or Reply and Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive bound up in one Book, in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> were printed in a Paper, to which was put the Names of ſeven Brethren, who in that Paper determined, <hi>That none of the Members of the Churches do buy, give or diſperſe any of theſe Books, (ſay they) aforeſaid under writ.</hi> But as my Name was not at all mentioned in that printed Paper, ſo there was no particular matter or thing charged in it on me, or any of my Books, in wrong to any Perſon or Books whatſoever. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, in the ſame printed Paper, thoſe ſeven Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren did there own, that they had not ſeen my Books, which they had there cenſured, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that I ſhould call them in, and leave them to their diſpoſe, inſomuch as it does appear that this ſower contrivance (of foiſting the Names of my Books in at the end of that Paper, which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175969:20"/>propely concerned other Perſons and Books there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in named, and not mine, which they own they had not then ſeen) was not to relieve Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> and Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> from any wrong done to them by me, or any of my Books, but to ſtifle my Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for the truth that was then coming forth, in my large Reply to Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s <hi>Breach repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and that his Abuſive Book might have the freer courſe to advance their ſinging among the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Therefore I deſire it may be well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, whether there is any reaſon to believe that I was ſelf-condemned for falſly accuſing Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Collins,</hi> when thoſe ſeven Brethren in their printed paper laid no particular matter or thing, in wrong to any perſon, unto my charge: Nor does Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> in his Defence pretend they did. What reaſon then is there to imagine, that at the ſame time I ſhould in apparent wrong to my ſelf, condemn my ſelf? eſpecially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that as ſoon as I could (after I had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that my Books were ſo abuſed in that paper by thoſe ſeven Brethren) I drew up and print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome Remarks on it, in vindication of my ſelf, and to clear my Books from that Injuſtice, which Remarks have never yet been anſwered. Surely therefore this carries a demonſtration that I was not ſelf-condemned, and that Mr <hi>Collins</hi>'s Aſſertion of it is a contrived Lye, a Confirmation whereof you have as follows.</p>
            <p>AT the Requeſt of Mr. <hi>Iſaac Marlow,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired me to teſtifie what I remember of what paſt in the General Aſſembly of the Meſſengers of the Baptized Churches, in they year 1692. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, I do hereby declare, that I do remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175969:21"/>there was then ſome Diſcourſe that paſs'd from him and Mr. <hi>William Collins,</hi> about ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Difference between them two: But I do not remember that there was any thing ſpoken to Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> aforeſaid, by the Elders and Brethren then preſent, by which it might ſeem as if they judged him ſelf-condemned: And I do believe they did not ſee any reaſon to charge him with the ſame, neither was there any concluſion made by them againſt him, tending to any ſuch thing; for had there been ſuch an apprehenſion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion about him, it would be inſerted in the Narrative of their Proceedings, that was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed of that Aſſembly; in which all that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe it will ſe there was no ſuch thing charged on him. In Witneſs whereof I have ſet my Hand this <hi>29th.</hi> of the <hi>8th.</hi> Month, 1696.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Kiffin.</hi> [a Paſtor]</p>
            <p>THeſe are to certifie whom it may concern, that I was at the Aſſembly of Elders and Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers held at <hi>Devonſhire-ſquare</hi> Meeting Houſe, in the year 1692. and heard the matter indifference debated between Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> and Mr. <hi>Iſaac Marlow,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> did ſtand firmly to what he had written and printed in his Book. And I alſo declare, that I do not remember that I heard Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> ſay any thing in order to Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; (had there been ſuch a thing declared by him, I do not queſtion but I ſhould have heard it fully improved againſt him) nor that the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly or any part who acted by the Authority of the whole, did charge Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> or any of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175969:21"/>his Books, with doing any wrong to any Perſon or Books whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Witneſs my Hand <hi>Octob.</hi> 10. 1696.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hugh Smith.</hi> [a Miniſter]</p>
            <p>WHeras it is deſired that we ſhould give ſome brief account in relation to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular caſe concerning Mr. <hi>Iſaac Marlow</hi>'s being ſelf-condemned at an Aſſembly of Elders and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers at <hi>Devonſhire-ſquare</hi> Meeting Houſe, in the year 1692. for falſly charging Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> with a falſe tranſlation of ſome Latine, we do hereby teſtifie, that we were in that Aſſembly, where we heard Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> mention ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning Mr. <hi>Timme,</hi> and a falſe tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a piece of Latine, which he ſaid was the Printers fault; but tho' we were there concerned as Meſſengers and Members of that Aſſembly, yet we know of nothing that paſſed there from Mr. <hi>Iſaac Marlow,</hi> that had any tendence to his ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemnation; but contrary wiſe the ſaid Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> did ſtrongly perſiſt in his own vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And we farther teſtifie, that that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, nor any part thereof, that acted by their appointment, did neither charge Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> nor any of his Books, with any particular thing in wrong to any Perſon or Books whatſoever that we remember.</p>
            <p>Witneſs our Hands, <hi>Robert Steed.</hi> [a Paſtor] <hi>John Scot.</hi> [a Paſtor]</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:175969:22"/>
            <p>I Being deſired, have here drawn up the truth of what I know concerning the caſe of Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> aſſerts that Mr. <hi>Iſaac Marlow</hi> was under, and I teſtifie as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>viz.</hi> That I was at the Aſſembly of Elders and Meſſengers, at <hi>Devonſhire-ſquare</hi> Meeting-Houſe, in the year 1692. where on Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> and Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach</hi>'s Reflections on Mr. <hi>Iſaac Marlow,</hi> the ſaid Mr. <hi>Mnrlow</hi> did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire that his Books might be examined, and did there freely promiſe, that if they could ſhew, that he had done any wrong to any, or committed any miſtake, he would make full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; but no particular abuſe or wrong was alledged by the aforeſaid Aſſembly, or any act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by their Order againſt the ſaid Mr. <hi>Marlow,</hi> who there ſtood firmly and inſtantly in his own vindication: And in all the frequent converſe I have had with him, both before and ſince, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found any thing like ſelf-condemnation in him about thoſe things; and therefore I great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wonder that Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> ſhould dare to aſſert that Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> was ſelf-condemned, ſeeing all his words and actions ſhewed plainly and abſolutely the contrary: I cannot therefore but conclude, that that aſſertion of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> is an untruth, againſt the Light of his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for which great Evil I deſire the Lord would give him true repentance.</p>
            <p>Witneſs my Hand, <hi>Octob.</hi> 12. 1696.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke Leader.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:175969:22"/>
            <p>Moreover, this Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> (with an other Perſon) is named in the aforeſaid printed Paper, as one that was to Anſwer for the ſlander rais'd on our firſt Baptized Churches, in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to Mr. <hi>Robert Steed</hi>'s Epiſtle, where it's ſaid, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. <q>We ask you whether or no generally the ſame Baptized Churches, in thoſe times, did not as unanimouſly conclude, and declare it too, that for a Goſpel Miniſter to have a yearly allowance, or a competent maintenance, was an humane Invention, and Antichriſtian? We ſpeak in part upon our own knowledge, and by good Information we have had from others, that both thoſe Goſpel Duties and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances were equally decryed;</q> (<hi>viz.</hi> Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with voices together, and Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance)</p>
            <p>To this Mr. <hi>William Kiffin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Steed,</hi> Mr. <hi>George Barrat,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Edward Man,</hi> anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Paſtors of Churches, in their printed Anſwer, <hi>page</hi> 17, 18. ſay, To this Charge we anſwer, <q>That nothing can be more falſly aſſerted, or more ſlanderouſly uttered: —What the judgment of thoſe Churches in their firſt conſtitution was, concerning the maintenance of Miniſters, may be ſeen in the <hi>38th.</hi> Article, (of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, printed in the year 1644.) in theſe Words,</q> 
               <hi>We do believe that the due main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Miniſters ſhould be the free and voluntary communication of the Church, that according to Chriſts Ordinance, they that preach the Goſpel ſhould live on the Goſpel,</hi> &amp;c. Likewiſe at the end of my print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Narrative nine other Brethren have cited this Article out of thoſe Churches Confeſſion of Faith, and have given their publick Teſtimony
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175969:23"/>againſt the aforeſaid Slander, which was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed with the Authority of Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi>'s name, but he by his own agreement oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf as a Perſon particularly to anſwer for it, as appears in the aforeſaid printed Paper, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thoſe ſeven Brethren condemn'd that ſlander as a great wrong to the firſt baptized Churches: And I ſee no reaſon why Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> as well as his Fellow Singer, that was equally concerned with him, ſhould not have been required, as he was, to make the ſame acknowledgment of his Error. And if Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> ſhould ſay, that he was not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make an acknowledgment of his evil in that ſlander, becauſe the fault was the other Perſons alone, and therefore it was laid on him only: I anſwer, that Mr. <hi>Collins, &amp;c.</hi> in that ſlander ſays, <hi>We ſpeak in part upon our own knowledge, and by good information we have had from others,</hi> &amp;c. which being expreſt in the plural number, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes more than one Perſon; and Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> having ſubmitted himſelf as the other, to anſwer for it, he muſt alſo be taken for one of the two principal Authors of that Slander, which was condemned as aforeſaid. So that had thoſe ſeven Brethren been more impartial, (ſome of whom I believe are ſincere Chriſtians, tho' ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized and drawn aſide to cover the deſigns of ſubtile heads for ſinging) we might have had leſs occaſion now to have treated on theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>Which to conclude, ſeeing Mr. <hi>William Collins,</hi> for the ſake of his Singing-worſhip, has made himſelf guilty of ſo foul a ſlander on our firſt baptized Churches, 'tis the leſs wonder that I and ſome of my Authors ſhould meet with ſuch
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:175969:23"/>evil Treatment from him; and to find his name (with his four Companions) to recommend Mr. <hi>Allens</hi> aforeſad Cheat about the Hebrew Rhime, and to other unfair matters: For which publick Failings, and all other Sins, I deſire he may have the Grace of true Repentance given to him, that his ſins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhment ſhall come from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Moreover, Foraſmuch as Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> and his five Companions have ſo far followed the Steps of their Fellow-Champions that went before them in this controverſie, as to ſet their Names in print, (as before is ſhewed) to ſuch Deceit and Error, that cannot be juſtified by any of them, I think our People have no reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard their writings of it, nor to credit their publick Teſtimonies. And I hope thoſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that are particularly concern'd, will in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Chriſt, and for Truths ſake, diſcourage that Spirit of Deceit and Lying, that has appear'd in defence of the common way of ſinging, and is an evident ſign of its being falſe Worſhip, that ſo the failings of particular Perſons may not become their Churches Sin and Shame unto Poſterity: And that they and other Churches will be watchful againſt the miſchief of falſe Worſhip, even where it is not practiſed. For while any of our Churches which do not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice the common way of ſinging, hold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion at the Lords Table knowingly, with any of their Members that practiſe it with other People, ſuch Churches defile their Separation in the ſame nature as if they had Communion with a whole Church that practiſed the ſame,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175969:24"/>and lay a foundation of Ruin to their own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formanion from falſe worſhip; for if it be lawful by the Word of God, for a Church to have ſuch full Communion knowingly with one Perſon that practiſeth falſe Worſhip with other Chriſtians, why not with ten Perſons, and with a whole Church that practiſeth the ſame Worſhip? and if this be lawful, then why may they not ſo hold Communion with the ſame falſe Worſhip (or with falſe Worſhippers reſpecting that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar) practiſed in their own Church, as well as with another Church that is in the practice of it. So that the natural conſequence if follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of a Churches allowing full Communion at the Lords Table with one perſon that practiſeth falſe Worſhip, leads to the bringing of it into uſe among themſelves, and ſo to ruin their Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reformation. And if any ſay, that ſuch a ſtrict Diſcipline as I am for, will hazard the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or dividing of many of our Churches about <hi>London:</hi> My Anſwer is, That if ſo, 'tis chiefly to be attributed to our ſinging Elders and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that have ſo far corrupted them, that they cannot bear a thorough Separation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and then we may ſee what ſad work they have made among us. The Lord awaken his People unto Righteouſneſs, and ſupply the want of true Reformers, that I and others who have walked in Church Communion for many years, which at preſent are unſetled, may to our Comfort in the Boſom of a pure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly conſtituted Church of Chriſt, leave this World when our appointed time is come.</p>
            <p>And that none of our Churches may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conduct of ſuch a Treacherous Popiſh
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:175969:24"/>Principle of the Liberty and Power of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Church, as appears in Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> and his five Companions, which does not only caſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon the Sufferings of the Saints for Reformation in Divine Worſhip, but openly confronts the Confeſſions of the Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters in this Nation, and is a ſhame unto thoſe ſix Miniſters that have broach'd it among the Baptiſts Churches.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iſaac Marlow.</signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>
                     <hi>December</hi> 1. 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
